Ankur Gupta

Software Engineering

New York, NY - Email me on Indeed: indeed.com/r/Ankur-Gupta/acbacddf87fcfc17

Over 10 years of software engineering and management experience with web applications, mobile applications, service oriented middleware and solution architecture.

As the Head of software engineering at LittleBits Electronics Inc., responsible for the e-commerce platform, upcoming mobile apps and team building. Additional technical leadership experience with building and leading the engineering team (on and off shore) for the mobile business unit at Fareportal Inc., a top 3 travel e-commerce organization.

Hands-on development and architecture for the Trusted Contacts iOS app, Zagat iOS and watchOS app, and Dining web-app at Google Inc., and for the "My Verizon" suite of customer account management applications across various mobile platforms including iOS, Android and Blackberry. Prior experience includes several engineering and research projects over 6 years.

Authorized to work in the US for any employer

WORK EXPERIENCE

Software Engineer

Google Inc. - New York, NY - April 2015 to Present

- Development of the dining web-app in the search stack.
- Architecture and development of the Trusted Contacts iOS application.
- Architecture and development for the Zagat iOS and watchOS application.
- Design and development of the core application architecture, data and caching layer, notifications framework, and several UI components.
- Development of several backend API, including work with the S2 library.

VP - Software Engineering

LittleBits Electronics Inc - New York, NY - June 2014 to November 2014

- Head of software engineering for the e-commerce platform.
- Lead major revamp of the e-commerce platform, including the customer facing web-portal, improvements to the backend CMS, inventory and product management system, and application hosting move to AWS.
- Architected and developed the recommender and up-sell engine.
- Implementation and evangelization of AGILE/SCRUM software engineering practices and streamlined the software development and QA processes.

Senior Director - Software Engineering

Fareportal Inc - January 2011 to May 2014

- Wrote the initial versions of the mobile applications and frameworks, and lead the expansion across mobile websites and apps for iPhone, iPad, Android.
- Hands-on participation with ramping up server and client technology frameworks, while addressing scalability and performance concerns, and longer term technology value for the end product.
- Architected solutions for SMS delivery, flight schedule change notification and re-booking, caching
 architecture for fare alerts, in-app chat services, push notifications based marketing and landing page
 framework, multi-lingual framework, framework for running multiple marketing sweepstakes, and overall

MVC based application architecture.

- Developed an innovative learning and result filtering algorithm for the Geneo application. Additionally, developed algorithms for recommending best fit alternate flights when there are flight delays and cancellations.
- Streamlined the SEM/SEO landing page technical strategy for the mobile websites, addressed page load
 optimization, analyzed performance trade-offs with responsive versus adaptive solutions and thin versus rich
 content.
- Lead the integration of third party solutions for application crash analysis, tracking downloads, engagement metrics, web-service performance and availability monitoring, and in-app payment services.
- Devised the QA strategy for coverage for multitude of device OS and hardware combinations, helped with the integration of the automation testing tools and building the QA automation strategy.

Consulting Software Engineering Lead

Verizon Wireless Inc. - October 2008 to January 2011

- Hands on architecture and development of "MyVerizon" suite of applications across various mobile platforms including Blackberry, Android, iOS
- Designed and developed the base MVC based framework that governs various application modules. The architecture was re-used for applications across various device Operating systems.
- Conceived and developed innovative widgets such as Drive Safe. The Drive Safe widget intercepts incoming calls, text messages and emails when a user is driving or busy and provides a custom auto reply. Experimented with auto-detecting when a user a driving based on the GPS readings

Research and Development Internship

Bell Labs - June 2008 to September 2008

- Contributed towards research, architecture and development of the Geo-pepper geographical messaging platform for location based content delivery.
- Designed and implemented a location-aware cache that reduces memory load and CPU-processing by storing

data relevant to user's current location.

• Contributed to the design of an efficient algorithm for reducing the number of location lookups on the client and automatically updating location lookup frequency. Implemented the design on the Blackberry OS.

Software Engineering Lead

Cressanda Solutions Limited - January 2000 to June 2002

- Lead a team building web based business software solutions.
- Developed the BridgeTrak Suite of applications/that provide solutions for issue management and resolutions to Help Desks, Call Centers and Technical support departments.
- Developed the iSever desktop product built upon MS Visio and other MS office offerings. iServer is a cloud based collaboration solution for MS office documents.

EDUCATION

Ph.D. (ABD) in Computer Science

New Jersey Institute of Technology - Newark, NJ 2005 to 2008

MS in Computer Science

New Jersey Institute of Technology - Newark, NJ 2003 to 2005

BS in Computer Science

Guru Nanak Dev University 1996 to 1999

LINKS

https://github.com/ankur0009/ProductPortfolio

ADDITIONAL INFORMATION

Languages (Significant Experience): Java, Objective-C

Languages (Some Experience): Go, Ruby

Front-end Technologies: HTML5, JavaScript, Bootstrap, Foundation (ZURB), Angular

Frameworks : Spring, Hibernate, Ruby on Rails

Databases: My SQL, PostgreSQL, Oracle, MS-SQL Server

Web-Servers : Apache Tomcat, WebSphere, IIS

Hosting Environments : AWS EC2, AWS RDS, Rackspace